A Guide to the Records of War Memorial Chapel, 1949-1985, 2001, undated
Special Collections, Virginia Tech
Special Collections, Virginia Tech
Records of War Memorial Chapel, 1949-1985, 2001, undated
Special Collections, Virginia Tech, Blacksburg, Va.
RG 6/3/9
8.2 Cubic Feet; 6 boxes, 2 oversize folders
The Records of War Memorial Chapel contain architectural records, posters, photographs, and prints pertaining to Virginia Tech's War Memorial Chapel - including the Memorial Court, pylons, and cenotaph - and its construction in the 1950s and early 1960s. There are also a few pamphlets detailing the dedication and commemoration of the chapel, as well as records from the chapel after it was opened.
Virginia Polytechnic Institute
Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
Virginia Polytechnic Institute. War Memorial Chapel
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
The collection is open for research.
Some documents are restricted for 75 years from date of creation in accordance with the Family Education Rights and Privacy Act and Virginia Tech Special Collections' policy regarding confidential information and privacy. Contact Special Collections for more information.
Acquisition Information
Records of War Memorial Chapel were transferred to Special Collections prior to 1980. Additional materials were transferred in October 1989.
Historical Note
Construction on the War Memorial Chapel started in spring 1951 and completed in May 1960, with renovations undertaken in 2000 to 2001. Initial funding was raised by alumni to build a non-denominational religious building on campus and memorial to alumni who died while serving in the United States Armed Forces. The sculpture inside was designed by Donald DeLue. It is a popular location for weddings and other events.
The Memorial Court on the chapel roof includes the iconic Pylons etched with the names of every Virginia Tech student and graduate who died in service, starting with World War I. The four left pylons - Brotherhood, Honor, Leadership, and Sacrifice - were designed by Henry Kries and the right pylons - Service, Loyalty, Duty, and Ut Prosim - by Charles Rudy. At the center of the Court, the cenotaph has the names of the Medal of Honor recipients who attended Virginia Tech.
The carillon purchased as part of the War Memorial Chapel fund was installed in Burruss Hall in 1957. An electronic carillon was donated by the Class of 1958 and installed in 1997.
Sources:
Young, Denise. "Hear ye, the bells of Burruss." In Virginia Tech magazine, Spring 2011. Accessed December 3, 2019. https://www.vtmag.vt.edu/spring11/feature2.html
Virginia Tech. "Virginia Tech Buildings: War Memorial Chapel." VT.edu. Accessed December 3, 2019. https://vt.edu/about/locations/buildings/war-memorial-chapel.html
Scope and Content
The Records of War Memorial Chapel contain architectural records, posters, photographs, and prints pertaining to Virginia Tech's War Memorial Chapel - including the Memorial Court, pylons, and cenotaph - and its construction in the 1950s and early 1960s. There are also a few pamphlets detailing the dedication and commemoration of the chapel, as well as records from the chapel after it was opened. The collection is arranged into four series.
Series I: Pictures and Sketches is made up of information from the construction of War Memorial Chapel, including the Memorial Court. There are small plan sheets, pictures of the sculpture models, newspaper clippings, and photographs of the construction process. Items also document when the Chapel was commemorated and dedicated and include prints of the Chapel and the Drillfield.
Series II: Blueprints includes reinforcing steel plans, chapel floor plans, elevation plans, and detail plans for the exterior opening, limestone bench, electrical details, and door and window openings. Most of the blueprints are dated January 14, 1950, but there are also some dated November 1, 1950, and February 19-20, 1951.
Series III: Oversize Sketches, Concept Prints, and Posters contains 3-D rendering concepts of War Memorial Court, a poster of photographs of the half-sized sculpture models for War Memorial Court, oversize photos of War Memorial Court, a folder of scale drawings for the memorial and oversize sketches of War Memorial Chapel.
Series IV: Chronological Files includes letters, reports, calendars, and other files from the chapel. Additionally, there are wedding applications and confidential documents, which are restricted.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into four series:
Series I: Pictures and Sketches
Series II: Blueprints
Series III: Oversize Sketches, Concept Prints, and Posters
Series IV: Chronological Files
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Related Materials
A model sculpture of Sacrifice, one of the Pylon statues, is in the Artifact Collection.
For architectural records of other Virginia Tech buildings, see Virginia Tech Buildings Architectural Collection, RG 6/3/2e.
Index Terms
Subjects:
University Archives; University History
Genres:
Blueprints; Posters; Sketches
Organizations:
Virginia Polytechnic Institute; Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University; Virginia Polytechnic Institute. War Memorial Chapel
Contents List
- Series I: Pictures and Sketches, 1949-1950, 1952, 1955-1957, 1960, 1962, 2001, undated
  - War Memorial Plans and Pictures Summary, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Chapel Plan Scheme 13, 1949-04-21 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Montague-Belts Company Material Sheets, 1950-10-09, 1950-11-27 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - War Memorial Court and Chapel Sketches, 1955-1956, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Photographs of Casts for War Memorial Chapel Sculptures, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Chapel Sculpture Models Photographs, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Photographs of Half Size Sculpture Models for Upper Level - Small Posters, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Photographs of Half Sized Sculpture Models, 1950-11-21, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Sacrifice Prints, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Memorial Court Prints, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Small War Memorial Chapel Prints, undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - View of Drillfield and Burruss Prints, undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Memorial Court Construction and Completed Small Photographs, 1954-1956, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Memorial Court Construction and Completed Large Photographs, 1952, undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Various Reports on War Memorial, 1952, 1977, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - War Memorial Newspaper Clippings, 1960, 1964, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - National Sculpture Review, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Ad for War Memorial, undated (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - War Memorial Chapel Improvements, 1960, 1999, 2001 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - "Memorial Supplement" Booklets, undated (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - War Memorial Dedications, 1960-05-29,2001-08-2001-09 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - War Memorial Chapel Commemoration Booklets, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - War Memorial Chapel Order of Worship Booklets, 1962-12-06-1963-03-31 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - War Memorial Planning and Financing Brochures, undated (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Booklets About War Memorial, undated (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Pylons Name Engravings, 1978-01 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Hammond's Printing and Litho Works Note, 1957-05-31 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Indiana Limestone Company Booklet, undated (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Roster of War Memorial Contributors Card Sketch, undated (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - From Office of Publication VPI Bulletin, undated (Box 1, Folder 30)
- Series II: Blueprints, 1950-01-14-1951-02-20
  - VPI War Memorial Reinforcing Steel Plans, 1950-11-22 (Box 2)
  - Northwest Elevation and Partial Southeast Elevation (Sheet 6), 1950-01-14 (Box 3)
  - Plot Plan (Sheet 1), 1950-01-14 (Box 3)
  - Chapel Plans (Sheet M-2), 1950-01-14 (Box 3)
  - Northeast Elevation (Sheet 5), 1950-01-14 (Box 3)
  - Southwest Elevation (Sheet 7), 1950-01-14 (Box 3)
  - Chapel Floor Plan, Memorial Court Plan, and Details (Sheet E-2), 1950-01-14 (Box 4)
  - Structural Plans and Details (Sheet S1), 1950-01-14 (Box 4)
  - Details of Branch Steam Tunnel (Sheet M4), 1950-01-14 (Box 4)
  - Transverse Sections (Sheet 3), 1950-01-14 (Box 4)
  - Longitudinal Section (Sheet 4), 1950-01-14 (Box 4)
  - Plot Plan and Electrical Details (Sheet ME-1), 1950-01-14 (Box 5)
  - Details (Sheet M-3), 1950-01-14 (Box 5)
  - Details of Exterior Opening (Sheet 10), 1951-02-19 (Box 6)
  - Details at Steps No. 1 (Sheet 8), 1950-11-01 (Box 6)
  - Limestone Bench Details/Roofing and Flashing Details (Sheet 13), 1951-02-19 (Box 6)
  - Limestone Details (Sheet 14), 1951-02-20 (Box 6)
  - Full Size Details of Door Opening 14 and Adjacent Window (Sheet 11), 1951-02-19 (Box 6)
  - Full Size Details of Door Opening 13 (Sheet 12), 1951-02-19 (Box 6)
  - Concrete Details (Sheet 9), 1950-11-01 (Box 6)
- Series III: Oversize Sketches, Concept Prints, and Posters, undated
  - Oversize 3-D Rendering Concepts of War Memorial Court, undated (Folder 1)
  - Photographs of Half-Sized Sculpture Models for Upper Level - Big Poster, undated (Folder 1)
  - Oversize Photos of War Memorial Court, undated (Folder 2)
  - Folder of Scale Drawings for the Memorial, undated (Folder 2)
  - Oversize Sketches of War Memorial Chapel, undated (Folder 2)
- Series IV: Chronological Files, 1960-1985
  - War Memorial Chapel Records, 1960-1967 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - War Memorial Chapel Correspondence, 1973-1974 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - War Memorial Chapel Information, 1973-1974, 1977 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - War Memorial Chapel Records, 1979-01 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - War Memorial Chapel Records, 1979-02 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - War Memorial Chapel Records, 1979-03 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - War Memorial Chapel Records, 1979-04 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - War Memorial Chapel Records, 1979-05 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - War Memorial Chapel Records, 1979-06 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - War Memorial Chapel Records, 1979-07 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - War Memorial Chapel Records, 1979-08 (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - War Memorial Chapel Records, 1979 (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - War Memorial Chapel Records, 1981 (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - War Memorial Chapel Records, 1982 (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - Weddings in War Memorial Chapel, 1985 (Box 7, Folder 15)
  - Restricted documents
    - War Memorial Chapel Records, 1960-1967 (Box 8, Folder 1)
      Access Restrictions
      Restricted 75 years from date
    - Wedding Application Forms, 1968 (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - Wedding Application Forms, 1969 (Box 8, Folder 3)
      Restricted 75 years from date.
    - Wedding Application Forms, 1970 (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - Wedding Application Forms, 1970-1971 (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - Wedding Application Forms, 1971 (Box 8, Folder 6)
    - Wedding Application Forms, 1972 (Box 8, Folder 7)
    - Wedding Application Forms, 1973 (Box 8, Folder 8)
    - Wedding Application Forms, 1974 (Box 8, Folder 9)
    - Wedding Application Forms, 1975 (Box 8, Folder 10)
    - Wedding Application Forms, 1976 (Box 8, Folder 11)
    - Wedding Application Forms, 1977 (Box 8, Folder 12)
    - Wedding Application Forms, 1976-1978 (Box 8, Folder 13)
    - Wedding Application Forms, 1977-1978 (Box 8, Folder 14)
    - Wedding Application Forms, 1978 (Box 8, Folder 15-16)
    - Wedding Application Forms, 1978-1979 (Box 8, Folder 17)
    - War Memorial Chapel Records, 1979-01 (Box 8, Folder 18)
    - War Memorial Chapel Records, 1979-02 (Box 8, Folder 19)
    - War Memorial Chapel Records, 1979-03 (Box 8, Folder 20)
    - War Memorial Chapel Records, 1979-04 (Box 8, Folder 21)
    - War Memorial Chapel Records, 1979-05 (Box 8, Folder 22)
    - War Memorial Chapel Records, 1979-06 (Box 8, Folder 23)
    - War Memorial Chapel Records, 1979-07 (Box 8, Folder 24)
    - War Memorial Chapel Records, 1979-08 (Box 8, Folder 25)
    - War Memorial Chapel Records, 1979 (Box 8, Folder 26)
    - War Memorial Chapel Records, 1981 (Box 8, Folder 27)
    - War Memorial Chapel Records, 1982 (Box 8, Folder 28)
    - Wedding Application Forms, 1981, 1983-1984 (Box 8, Folder 29)
    - Weddings in War Memorial Chapel, 1985 (Box 8, Folder 30)